<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Jitesh117</title>
    <link>//localhost:1313/musings/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Jitesh117</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 29 Apr 2024 18:01:41 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="//localhost:1313/musings/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Do We Really Know Ourselves?</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/musings/do-we-really-know-ourselves/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Apr 2024 18:01:41 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/musings/do-we-really-know-ourselves/</guid>
      <description>One of the most haunting realisations I&amp;rsquo;ve had about myself recently is that I&amp;rsquo;ve let my work define me too much all my life. Like, barring some very close friends, none could pinpoint anything about my personality.
If you&amp;rsquo;d asked anyone from my class about me, the most they could tell about me was that &amp;ldquo;Jitesh likes reading a lot&amp;rdquo;. That&amp;rsquo;s it. Although it&amp;rsquo;s not the people&amp;rsquo;s perception about me what&amp;rsquo;s bothering me, but the fact that I don&amp;rsquo;t do much apart from my work is troubling me a lot now.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why Reading Fiction Matters</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/musings/why-reading-fiction-matters/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2024 19:34:46 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/musings/why-reading-fiction-matters/</guid>
      <description>Being in Tech, more often than not, if you ask anyone for book recommendations, they&amp;rsquo;d recommend a non-fiction self-help book. Although non-fiction books have their place, Fiction should never be overlooked.
One thing which makes Fiction books overlooked by the general population is that there is no direct benefit of reading them. When you&amp;rsquo;ve read a non-fictional book, you get know some new knowledge. But that&amp;rsquo;s not the case with Fiction books.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Trap of Knowing What You Want</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/musings/the-trap-of-knowing-what-you-want/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Apr 2024 14:27:45 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/musings/the-trap-of-knowing-what-you-want/</guid>
      <description>In our world, we often think that finding our passion and purpose is the key to being happy. But this can actually be a trap. Many people think they know what they want, and they chase after those things, believing they will finally feel satisfied. But then they end up feeling lost and unfulfilled anyway.
Having a clear idea of what you desire can be powerful. But we have to be careful, because this mindset also has its limits.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Making and Losing Friends</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/musings/making-and-losing-friends-in-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Apr 2024 15:47:15 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/musings/making-and-losing-friends-in-life/</guid>
      <description>Friends are the one thing that can change the outlook of anything that is happening in our lives. Having their mere presence can amplify any happiness.
Growing up as a kid whose father worked in the Indian Air Force, I had to switch cities a lot. While it meant I got to make new friends every 3-5 years, it also meant losing most of my friends whenever I changed places. Each new transfer meant saying goodbye to old friends and diving into a new adventure.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
