<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Jitesh117</title>
    <link>//localhost:1313/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Jitesh117</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 26 May 2024 19:14:04 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="//localhost:1313/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>How To Last Longer in Head</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/musings/how-to-last-longer-in-head/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 May 2024 19:14:04 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/musings/how-to-last-longer-in-head/</guid>
      <description>Having a short attention span makes it difficult to get things done. You might start an important project, but then get sidetracked checking Instagram or replying to a text message. Before you know it, hours have gone by and you haven&amp;rsquo;t made much progress.
With all the digital distractions these days, Attention Span has become a currency whose exchange rate has never been higher.
You must have searched the web, desperately trying to find a one-size-fits-all formula to get better at focusing.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mute, Block Even</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/musings/mute-block-even/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 May 2024 21:27:11 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/musings/mute-block-even/</guid>
      <description>There would be times, when you would see a post or a comment on Twitter, where you would really want to meet the person who posted it and punch them in their face. But alas, you can only reply to their post. But before you hit the SEND button, think, do you really want to feed the algorithm to show more similar things like this?
Twitter algorithm, like most social media platforms, is programmed to push whatever will get the most engagement from you, be it likes, comments or retweets.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Delude yourself to Greatness</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/musings/delulu-is-the-solulu/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 May 2024 16:00:29 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/musings/delulu-is-the-solulu/</guid>
      <description>One of the weird things I&amp;rsquo;ve witnessed in the tech world, is the skill-to-courage ratio in people. Contrary to popular belief, skill is still in abundance. What&amp;rsquo;s scarce though, is the belief in one&amp;rsquo;s own abilities.
The worst thing one can do, is to doubt themselves. You have to delude yourself everyday, that you can achieve anything you put your mind and soul to.
The amount of opportunities you can get just by being confident in yourself and putting your work out there, is unreal.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Roadmapping Your Way to Mediocrity</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/musings/roadmapping-your-way-to-mediocrity/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 May 2024 18:21:22 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/musings/roadmapping-your-way-to-mediocrity/</guid>
      <description>Tech, unlike other fields, changes its landscape every passing day. You can never tell what&amp;rsquo;s trending today will live to see the face of tomorrow or not.
Every other week, a person will emerge with their new shiny &amp;ldquo;Roadmap&amp;rdquo; of any particular domain in tech. Although the intention is right, these Roadmaps often over-simplify the complexity and dynamic nature of the tech ecosystem.
No matter how much one tries to bring order to this chaotic tech world, they fall flat on their face every single time.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Keyboard Is Mightier Than the Pen</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/musings/the-keyboard-is-mightier-than-the-pen/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 May 2024 19:55:34 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/musings/the-keyboard-is-mightier-than-the-pen/</guid>
      <description>Whether you like it or not, Computers are now an integral part of our lives. But is this for the better? That&amp;rsquo;s a discussion for another day.
And to make the most out of your computer, your hand needs to becomme one with our keyboard. Learning the tools at your disposal really makes a huge difference. I&amp;rsquo;ve covered how to get faster at typing in one of my previous posts.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>To Do, or to Be Perceived as Someone Who Does</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/musings/to-do-or-to-be-perceived-as-someone-who-does/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 May 2024 10:02:19 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/musings/to-do-or-to-be-perceived-as-someone-who-does/</guid>
      <description>Internet, like in real life, is filled with grifters, i.e. People who portray themselves as someone they aren&amp;rsquo;t.
Following the &amp;ldquo;Fake it till you make it&amp;rdquo; mindset, is a double edged sword, depending on the person. On one hand, it can motivate you to push your limits, on the other hand, it can lead to dishonesty and false pride in yourself.
The dopamine hit you get on your posts, makes it very lucrative to only post a particular kind of content, whether you genuinely enjoy it or not.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Triumph of the Nerds</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/musings/triumph-of-the-nerds/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 May 2024 19:18:38 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/musings/triumph-of-the-nerds/</guid>
      <description>The term &amp;lsquo;Nerd&amp;rsquo;, originally coined as a slur for overly intellectual, socially awkward individuals, is now worn as a badge of honor, but why?
You might think that the present-day nerds are somewhat evolved from their former counterparts, but you&amp;rsquo;d be wrong. The essence of being a nerd is still the same, what has changed is our perception of them.
What&amp;rsquo;s changed now, is that we can see the output of their nerdiness in real time, thanks to the internet boom.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to Twitter</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/musings/how-to-twitter/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 May 2024 19:05:45 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/musings/how-to-twitter/</guid>
      <description>For the longest time since I had created my twitter account, the only thing which I did was retweet and like. The reason I had created my account was to &amp;ldquo;Learn in public&amp;rdquo;. And that&amp;rsquo;s what I did in my initial days at twitter. Started doing the #100DaysOfCode challenge. Learnt a bunch of things from this. But after this ended, so did my twitter posts.
I didn&amp;rsquo;t know what to post.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Imposter Syndrome or Skill Issue</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/musings/imposter-syndrome-or-skill-issue/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 May 2024 18:59:37 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/musings/imposter-syndrome-or-skill-issue/</guid>
      <description>Whenever I see a youngling posting their project on twitter, it makes me wonder, why have I not done this myself ever? Do I just not have it in me what it takes to build good products?
Or I do have it in me but just don&amp;rsquo;t realise it. Whatever the reason is, the fact remains that I haven&amp;rsquo;t done anything worth noticing.
So what can I do to solve this issue?</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Perceptron</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/blog/perceptron/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 May 2024 15:43:31 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/blog/perceptron/</guid>
      <description>The perceptron is a foundational concept in machine learning, representing the simplest type of artificial neural network. This article explores the perceptron model, its functionality, and its significance in the world of Machine learning.
Introduction to the Perceptron The perceptron, developed by Frank Rosenblatt in 1957, is a type of linear classifier used for binary classification tasks. It is the basis of more complex neural networks and deep learning models.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>College Days</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/musings/college-days/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 May 2024 21:32:59 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/musings/college-days/</guid>
      <description>It was a rainy day of November, when I reached the Pondicherry Railway station with my Dad, excited as well as a little frightened. Loads of Auto walas were shouting &amp;ldquo;Bhaiyya, bhaiyya kidhar jana hai?&amp;rdquo; in their Tamil accent, trying to lure us using Hindi in the Tamil heavy environment. Even though we knew we were being ripped off, dad selected one and we put all of my stuff in the auto and told the driver to go to the &amp;ldquo;Enginerring college&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Curse of Dimensionality</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/blog/the-curse-of-dimensionality/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 May 2024 15:15:29 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/blog/the-curse-of-dimensionality/</guid>
      <description>As the number of features or dimensions grows in a dataset, the effectiveness of many machine learning algorithms can suffer from an issue called the &amp;ldquo;curse of dimensionality.&amp;rdquo; This problem is particularly prevalent for instance-based algorithms like K-nearest neighbors (KNN).
The KNN algorithm relies on calculating the distances between data points to determine which points are nearest neighbors.
In low dimensional spaces like 2D or 3D, the concepts of distance and neighborhood are relatively straightforward.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Serenity of Matri Mandir</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/musings/the-serenity-of-matri-mandir/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2024 21:43:05 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/musings/the-serenity-of-matri-mandir/</guid>
      <description>In the heart of Auroville, a township dedicated to Human Unity, stands Matri-Mandir, a monument that represents &amp;ldquo;The Mother&amp;rdquo;. This is not just an architectural wonder but a gateway to inner peace and spiritual awakening.
The inception of Auroville traces back to the spiritual vision of the Indian philosopher and guru Sri Aurobindo and his partner, known as &amp;ldquo;The Mother&amp;rdquo;. The Mother dreamed of establishing a universal township unlike anywhere else on earth - a place where people from all nations could live together in peace while undertaking an experiment in human unity and evolution.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why to Use Tmux</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/blog/why-to-use-tmux/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2024 16:22:06 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/blog/why-to-use-tmux/</guid>
      <description>1. Introduction tmux (Terminal Multiplexer) is a powerful terminal utility that allows you to create multiple terminal sessions, split windows, and detach and reattach sessions with ease. It&amp;rsquo;s a game-changer for anyone who works heavily in the terminal, providing a robust environment for multitasking, remote server management, and efficient workflow.
Benefits of using tmux Persistent sessions: Detach and reattach sessions, ensuring your work is never lost Efficient window and pane management: Split your terminal into multiple windows and panes Enhanced productivity: Streamline your workflow by running multiple commands simultaneously Remote session sharing: Share sessions with other users for collaboration or pair programming A Brief overview of its features tmux offers a wide range of features, including window and pane management, customizable status bars, key bindings, plugins, and more.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Do We Really Know Ourselves?</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/musings/do-we-really-know-ourselves/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Apr 2024 18:01:41 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/musings/do-we-really-know-ourselves/</guid>
      <description>One of the most haunting realisations I&amp;rsquo;ve had about myself recently is that I&amp;rsquo;ve let my work define me too much all my life. Like, barring some very close friends, none could pinpoint anything about my personality.
If you&amp;rsquo;d asked anyone from my class about me, the most they could tell about me was that &amp;ldquo;Jitesh likes reading a lot&amp;rdquo;. That&amp;rsquo;s it. Although it&amp;rsquo;s not the people&amp;rsquo;s perception about me what&amp;rsquo;s bothering me, but the fact that I don&amp;rsquo;t do much apart from my work is troubling me a lot now.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why Reading Fiction Matters</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/musings/why-reading-fiction-matters/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2024 19:34:46 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/musings/why-reading-fiction-matters/</guid>
      <description>Being in Tech, more often than not, if you ask anyone for book recommendations, they&amp;rsquo;d recommend a non-fiction self-help book. Although non-fiction books have their place, Fiction should never be overlooked.
One thing which makes Fiction books overlooked by the general population is that there is no direct benefit of reading them. When you&amp;rsquo;ve read a non-fictional book, you get know some new knowledge. But that&amp;rsquo;s not the case with Fiction books.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hierarchical Indexing in Pandas</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/blog/hierarchical-indexing-in-pandas/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Apr 2024 11:56:07 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/blog/hierarchical-indexing-in-pandas/</guid>
      <description>Working with high-dimensional or categorized data can be a complex and challenging task, but Pandas provides a powerful tool to simplify this process: hierarchical indexing.
Hierarchical indexing, also known as multi-level or multi-indexed indexing, allows you to create and manipulate indexes with multiple levels or dimensions, providing a more intuitive and organized way to structure, access, and analyze your data.
This indexing technique is particularly useful when dealing with datasets that contain multiple levels of categorization or grouping, such as data from different regions, periods, or product categories.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Activation Function and Loss Functions in Neural Networks</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/blog/activation-function-and-loss-functions-in-neural-networks/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Apr 2024 20:52:26 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/blog/activation-function-and-loss-functions-in-neural-networks/</guid>
      <description>Activation Functions in Neural Networks Activation functions are a crucial component of artificial neural networks, serving as the mathematical operation that determines the output of a node or neuron. They introduce non-linearities to the network, allowing it to learn complex patterns and relationships within the data.
1. Sigmoid Function Sigmoid function, also known as the logistic function. This function squashes input values between 0 and 1, making it a popular choice for the output layer in binary classification problems.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>So You Think You Know Git?</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/blog/so-you-think-you-know-git/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Apr 2024 14:39:34 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/blog/so-you-think-you-know-git/</guid>
      <description>This article is just about my learnings from the talk So you Think you know Git.
One might think that everything there is to know about Git has already been covered, but that would be wrong. Even today, the Git codebase is seeing around 9 commits per day and 10,000 commits in the last 3 years. That means there are still plenty of new things being added to Git that you might not know about.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Trap of Knowing What You Want</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/musings/the-trap-of-knowing-what-you-want/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Apr 2024 14:27:45 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/musings/the-trap-of-knowing-what-you-want/</guid>
      <description>In our world, we often think that finding our passion and purpose is the key to being happy. But this can actually be a trap. Many people think they know what they want, and they chase after those things, believing they will finally feel satisfied. But then they end up feeling lost and unfulfilled anyway.
Having a clear idea of what you desire can be powerful. But we have to be careful, because this mindset also has its limits.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Making and Losing Friends</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/musings/making-and-losing-friends-in-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Apr 2024 15:47:15 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/musings/making-and-losing-friends-in-life/</guid>
      <description>Friends are the one thing that can change the outlook of anything that is happening in our lives. Having their mere presence can amplify any happiness.
Growing up as a kid whose father worked in the Indian Air Force, I had to switch cities a lot. While it meant I got to make new friends every 3-5 years, it also meant losing most of my friends whenever I changed places. Each new transfer meant saying goodbye to old friends and diving into a new adventure.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Papers</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/shelf/papers/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Mar 2024 16:20:40 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/shelf/papers/</guid>
      <description> Attention is all you need Pre-train, Prompt and Recommendation: A Comprehensive Survey of Language Modelling Paradigm Adaptations in Recommender Systems </description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Articles</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/shelf/articles/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Mar 2024 16:20:20 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/shelf/articles/</guid>
      <description> Being a Noob by Paul Graham My GitHub Project went viral by Aditya Lenge How to keep yourself unblocked by Arpit Bhayani </description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Books</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/shelf/books/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Mar 2024 16:20:09 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/shelf/books/</guid>
      <description>Fiction 1984 by George Orwell By the River Piedra I sat down and wept by Paulo Coelho Animal Farm By George Orwell Halo The Forerunner Saga series by Greg Bear Non-fiction Show Your Work by Austin Kleon The Art of War by Sun Tzu The Psychology of Money by Morgan Housel Fooled by Randomness by Nassim Nicholas Taleb </description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How I Learned to Type 150&#43; WPM</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/blog/how-i-learned-to-type-fast/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Mar 2024 16:25:00 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/blog/how-i-learned-to-type-fast/</guid>
      <description>In this article I&amp;rsquo;m going to write about a topic very close to my heart, which is &amp;ldquo;How I Learned to type Faster&amp;rdquo;. Typing fast has been a game changer for me, and I believe anyone who types fast can become at least twice as productive as they already are.
But why bother to type fast? 1. It just really impresses people When people see me typing while coding, the single biggest compliment I&amp;rsquo;ve got is &amp;ldquo;Wow!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hash Tables Primer: The Ins and Outs of Efficient Key-Value Storage</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/blog/the-ins-and-outs-of-hash-tables/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2024 17:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/blog/the-ins-and-outs-of-hash-tables/</guid>
      <description>Hash Tables are one of the most used Data structures, they&amp;rsquo;re so popular that almost every language has their own implementation and nomenclature of Hash Tables.
One very interesting fact about Hash Tables is that they&amp;rsquo;re also used as building blocks for:
Classes and its members Variable lookup table As we can see, Hash Tables are not just used in the business case of any application, but it&amp;rsquo;s also used in the inner working of any programming language.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hash Table Performance and Implementation</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/blog/hash-table-performance-and-implementation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2024 15:34:47 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/blog/hash-table-performance-and-implementation/</guid>
      <description>Hash Table gives constant time performance when there are zero collisions.
But that&amp;rsquo;s impossible!
So how can we quantify how &amp;ldquo;full&amp;rdquo; the table is? This is called the Load Factor
Load Factor Load Factor is the ratio of the total number of elements and the number of slots in the hash table.
Load Factor with different resolution strategies Load Factor with different resolution strategies With chaining, we can never fill the table i.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why I use Vim and why you should too</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/blog/why-i-use-vim-and-why-you-should-too/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Mar 2024 07:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/blog/why-i-use-vim-and-why-you-should-too/</guid>
      <description>VIM or Vi Improved, is a free and open-source text editor for the terminal written by Bram Moolenaar. It is a highly powerful and versatile text editor that has managed to gather a devoted following among many people. Known for its efficiency, speed, and extensive customization options, Vim offers a unique modal editing approach that distinguishes it from traditional text editors.
Although I was familiar with Vim since 2020, I never thought of actually using it.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hyperparameter Tuning and Ensembling</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/blog/ensembling-and-hyperparameter-tuning/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Mar 2024 17:56:43 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/blog/ensembling-and-hyperparameter-tuning/</guid>
      <description>Ensembling, a powerful technique in machine learning, has gained widespread popularity for its ability to significantly enhance predictive performance. By combining the predictions of multiple individual models, ensembles can often achieve better results than any single model alone. However, to fully leverage the potential of ensembling, it&amp;rsquo;s crucial to fine-tune the hyperparameters of the underlying base models.
Hyperparameter tuning involves searching for the optimal combination of model parameters that maximizes performance metrics such as accuracy or F1 score.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
